Arnulfo D. Trejo Papers, 1955-2001
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Arnulfo D. Trejo Papers, 1955-2001
MS 515
Trejo, Arnulfo D.
The Arnulfo Trejo collection consists of Trejo's personal papers as well as materials related to REFORMA, the National Association to Promote Library and Information Services to Latino and the Spanish-speaking, and Hispanic Books Distributors Materials which he founded both organizations. Other noteworthy materials are his participation in Los Tucsonense, an organization committed to preserving el Barrio Historico neighborhood and El Tiradito in Tucson, AZ.
1 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccoll
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Arnulfo Duenes Trejo was born in Villa Vicente Guerrero, Durango, Mexico on August 15, 1922. His family immigrated to the U.S. when he was three. He spent his youth growing up in Barrio Libre in Tucson, Arizona, and attended Drachman Elementary, Safford Jr. High and Tucson High School.
Trejo served in the military during World War II, in the 143rd Infanty Division in the South Pacific, reaching the rank of sergeant. He received both the Purple Heart and a Bronze Star medal as well as Asiatic Pacific Services medal and the Phillipine Liberation Ribbon for his service. He became a U.S. citizen while enlisted, in 1944.
After the war, Trejo enrolled at the University of Arizona, where in 1949, he received his B.A. degree in Education. Shortly thereafter, in 1951, he earned an M.A. degree in Spanish Language and Literature from La Universidad de las Americas in Mexico City. By 1953, Trejo had also received a M.A. in Library Science from Kent State University. In 1959, he received his Doctor of Letters degree (with honors) from the National University of Mexico.
Trejo began his career as a librarian in Mexico in 1953. By 1955, he landed a position at UCLA as a reference librarian, followed by a four year stint as Assistant College Librarian at California State College at Long Beach. He also spent time directing the library for Stanford University’s Escuela de Administracion de Negocios para Graduados in Lima Peru. Upon his return to the United States, he worked for two years as Assistant Professor of Library Service at UCLA.
In 1966, Dr. Trejo was hired by the University of Arizona, where he served as Associate Professor of Library Science and Bibliographer for Latin American Collections. In 1968, he took a yearlong leave of absence to serve as a consultant for United States Agency for International Development (USAID) in Caracas, Venezuela. His connections to libraries and scholars in Latin America proved beneficial to the University of Arizona, as he helped build one of the richest collections of Latin American materials in the country.
Upon his return to the University of Arizona, Dr. Trejo spent time teaching a course in Mexican American literature. He was also a founding faculty member of the Graduate Library School, where he began teaching courses in Latin American Bibliography in 1970.
Dr. Trejo kept quite busy in the early 1970’s, both as an academic and as an activist. He was instrumental in organizing a community effort to save a downtown monument called “El Tiradito”, or the Wishing Shrine, from being torn down to make way for a new freeway. Trejo’s efforts helped place the shrine on the National Register of Historic Places in 1971. He remained active as a member of Los Tucsonenses, a community organization dedicated to preserving local Latino culture, throughout the 1970s.
Throughout his life he accomplished many things, but was best known for having founded REFORMA, The National Assocation for the Promotion of Library Services to the Spanish Speaking in 1971, and for creating the Graduate Library Institute for Spanish Speaking Americans at the University of Arizona’s Graduate Library School. Latino librarians throughout the country agree that Trejo was the “father of Latino librarianship.” His legacy is a rich one and his admirers are many.
Trejo founded REFORMA, the National Association of Spanish Speaking Librarians in the United States in 1971, and served as its president from 1971-1974. The organization is still in operation, and its purpose is to, among other things, provide a means for bilingual librarians to network with eachother, to promote the collection of Spanish-language materials in libraries, to advocate for the recruitment of Latinos to librarianship, and to provide programming that benefits the Latino community. The organization now has chapters in every corner of the US as well as in Puerto Rico and is now called, REFORMA: The National Asssociation for the Promotion of Library and Information Services to Latinos and the Spanish Speaking
In 1975, Trejo organized and administered the Graduate Library Institute for Spanish Speaking Americans (GLISA) a federally funded project that operated for four years under his direction. 56 individuals earned their master’s degrees in library science through this program. Many of these graduates went on to become directors of major library systems. Today’s Spectrum Scholar’s program, an American Library Association sponsored project, and the University of Arizona’s Knowledge River program were both modeled after GLISA.
In 1980, Dr. Trejo opened Hispanic Book Distributors, a book vending company specializing in books from the Spanish Speaking world, and dedicated to increasing the availability of Spanish language materials in U.S. libraries. Dr. Trejo particularly enjoyed making regular buying trips to Mexico, Spain and Argentina, and his materials were sold to public, school and academic libraries across the country.
Trejo retired from the University of Arizona Graduate Library School in 1984, a full professor, with a long list of accomplishments and publications.
In 1992, after the death of his second wife Annette M. Foster, Dr. Trejo founded the Trejo-Foster Foundation for Library Education, where he was able to continue to influence the library profession by providing educational institutes focused on library services to Latinos and the Spanish speaking.
Trejo died in Tucson, Arizona in 2002, at the age of 80.
Among Trejo’s publications they include: Bibliografia Chicana: A Guide to Information Resources, Gale, 1975, The Chicanos: As We See Ourselves, University of Arizona Press, 1979, (Trejo was editor), and Quien Es Quien: a who’s who of Spanish-speaking librarians in the United States, Hispanic Book Distributors, 1994.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Article and Short Story Manuscripts, 1955-1973, undated
Series II: Speeches, 1957-1977
Series III: Los Tucsonense / El Tiradito Organizational Files, 1970-1978
Series IV: Reforma Organizational Files, 1971-1981, 1996
Series V: Hispanic Books Distributors Materials, 1987-2001
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of early and final drafts of articles, essays, and reports authored by Arnulfo D. Trejo concerning the representation of Hispanics in the library profession as well as materials collected by United States libraries. This collection also contains drafts and finals drafts of short stories authored by Trejo which detail Hispanic culture. Also contained within the collection are materials from the Los Tucsonense and El Tiradito Organizations which strove to preserve Tucson's el Barrio Historico neighborhood. Materials from these organizations include correspondence, news releases, newspaper clippings, member rosters, newsletters, and other materials. The bulk of the collection is comprised of materials collected by Arnulfo D. Trejo during his tenure as president of REFORMA, the National Association to Promote Library and Information Services to Latino and the Spanish-speaking. These materials include REFORMA conference agendas / schedules, member presentations, correspondence, annual meeting attendance lists, organization evaluation forms, membership rosters, various forms, news releases, conference resolutions, meeting minutes, and other materials.
Access Terms
Trejo, Arnulfo D.
Library schools –Arizona--History
Library schools—Curricula
Hispanic American librarians
Hispanic Americans and libraries
Hispanic Americans and libraries—United States--Evaluation
Hispanic American neighborhoods—Arizona--Tucson
Historic sites—Arizona—Tucson
Historic districts—Arizona--Tucson
Container List
- Series I: Article and Short Story Manuscripts, 1955-1973, undated
  Series is arranged chronologically and contains early and final drafts as well as published versions of articles, studies, and reports authored by Arnulfo D. Trejo. Articles concern the technological advancements within the library profession, representation of the Hispanic community in United States libraries and educational system, and Latin-American Studies. Some of these materials include submission of publication correspondence. Folder 1 contains drafts of the narrative short story "Her Name was Linda." Folder 2 contains drafts of narrative short stories "Arroyo Seco", "The Fifteen Hundred Dollar Purse", and "The Good Humor Man."
  - 1955 – 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Speeches, 1957-1977
  Series is arranged chronologically and contains early and final drafts authored by Arnulfo D. Trejo, with some materials including correspondence. This series also contains research materials such as scholarly articles, newspapers articles, and reports. Folder 3 contains ephemera from the 1969 opening of the Valencia Branch Library, Tucson, AZ. Some materials are in Spanish.
  - 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III: Los Tucsonense / El Tiradito Organizational Files, 1970-1978
  Series is arranged chronologically and contains correspondence between organization members, news releases, expense reports, published articles, historical accounts, petitions, letters to public officials and organizational leaders, letters to local media, nomination forms for the Arizona State Register of Historic Sites, research materials, and other materials created by Los Tucsonense, an organization committed to preserving Tucson's el Barrio Historico neighborhood. The majority of the materials concern the activities of the El Tiradito Committee, also known as The Wishing Shrine Committee, an organization dedicated to preserving the Wishing Shrine historic landmark located in the el Barrio Historico neighborhood.
  - 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series IV: REFORMA Organizational Files, 1971-1981, 1996
  Series is arranged chronologically and contains materials collected by Arnulfo D. Trejo during his tenure as president and members of REFORMA. These materials include REFORMA conference agendas / schedules, member presentations, correspondence, annual meeting attendance lists, organization evaluation forms, membership rosters, various forms, news releases, conference resolutions, materials from Arnulfo D. Trejo's University of Arizona's English courses, meeting minutes, research materials, and newsletters. Some materials are in Spanish.
  - 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, January-May, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, June-December, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1974-1975, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - First Annual REFORMA National Conference Publication, August 22-25, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series V: Hispanic Books Distributors Materials, 1987-2001
  Series is arranged chronologically and contains printed bulletins and catalogs.
  - Hispanic Books Bulletin, vol. 1; no. 1-4, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hispanic Books Bulletin, vol. 2; no. 1-4, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hispanic Books Bulletin, vol. 3; no. 1-4, vol.4; no.1-2, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hispanic Books Bulletin, vol. 5; no.1-2, vol.6; 1-4, vol.7; no.1-2, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hispanic Books Distributors Catalogs, 1995, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)